Curriculum Vitae

Ivan Buendia Gayton

5702 Solly Road

Summerland, British Columbia

V0H 17.1

Canada

ivangayton@gmail.com

Phone: +1 604 356 1458

Overview:

I work in the vicinity of the intersection of technology, humanitarianism, health, and innovation.

I spent ten years in the hardest and most forgotten/neglected contexts of the world, and care deeply about making things better for the poorest and most vulnerable, often in the context of humanitarian aid, but also in technology and business. I'm a nerd with a keen interest in technology and some moderate coding ability (and perhaps more product management skill), a manager who likes empowering people to get on with what they're good at while keeping an eye on the important goals, a mapper with a preference for displays that inform immediate decision-making, an advocate for human-centred migration policy and remittances, a free software and open data evangelist, and a jack-of-many-trades but master of none.

I like solving real problems, and want to work with teams doing so.

Work Experience:

Wave.com

May 2016-April 2017

African operations and expansion for a mobile money and remittance startup

- Preparing licenses and other prerequisites for Wave's operations in West Africa, based in Dakar, Senegal.
- Successfully negotiated a bank partnership, Central Bank authorization, Value Added Service provider license, access to USSD and SMS with major telcos.
- Left Wave amicably after a major reorganization left no appropriate role for me compatible with my family's living circumstances (Wave is no longer focusing on West African expansion).

Independent consultant to several humanitarian agencies

October 2015-May 2016

Advisor, project manager, and software product manager

- Advising and to some extent leading an Electronic Medical Records for Emergencies development team (org)
- Ongoing support to humanitarian mapping initiative that I co-founded in 2014 (http://missingmaps.org)
 - Developing a software for off-line mobile image classification for humanitarian mapping (<u>com/mapswipe</u>)
- Development of an offline server for data collection in resource-poor settings (http://github.com/ivangayton/ODKAggregateOnEdison)
- Support to mobile data collection projects in several countries for humanitarian agencies

MSF-UK

GIS and Technological Innovation Advisor

- Intended to make maps for field projects, but found that the base data was simply missing. Founded (with Andrew Braye of the British Red Cross and Dale Kunce of the American Red Cross) the Missing Maps project to create the necessary base data. Thus far the Missing Maps has created free, open map data for nearly 20 million people. Areas of particular focus have been DRC, South Sudan, Bangladesh, West Africa, and Burundi. In particular the Katanga mission with MSF is making use of this data in practice.
- Led a collaboration with Google to create electronic medical records in Ebola centres. Created some nice hardware and software, but arrived too late to have any impact on patient care (lesson learned).
- Worked on UAV (drone) imagery collection; so far no field deployments due to my own caution about perception, but would love to follow up.
- Implemented off-line mobile data collection systems using OpenDataKit and cheap smartphones; this worked particularly well in Sierra Leone, albeit mostly for mapping. Support other agencies in learning to do this.
- Made an attempt at SMS-based health surveillance data collection in Nigeria; this was eventually piloted and found to be worth further investment though there are still wrinkles that need ironing out; this will be followed up by the current GIS officer at MSF-UK.

MSF Operational Centre Amsterdam (OCA)

January 2012 – April 2013

Head of Mission

Nigeria (based in Sokoto)

 Managing a mid-sized mission with an Emergency Response Unit and an environmental response – the Zamfara Lead Poisoning crisis Doing a lot of intense, and (I think) somewhat innovative advocacy aimed at getting the
government of Nigeria to take its responsibilities with regard to environmental remediation in
Zamfara state. This was quite successful; the government actually did a genuine cleanup in the
affected villages.

MSF-OCA

January 2011-Sept 2011

Humanitarian Affairs Advisor, with a specialization in migration-related issues.

- Tried to push MSF-OCA to be a bit more involved in the general migration context
- Wrote the a proposal for MSF-OCA to deploy a maritime response to the migrant context in the Mediterranean, which was not implemented at the time but subsequently helped shape the MSF-Sea response
- Responded to emergencies (somewhat) related to migration, including two months as Head of Mission for MSF-OCG in Tunisia/Libya at the outset of the Libyan insurgency, and an assessment/vaccination program in northern Chad for people fleeing southward from Libya.

MSF-OCA Haiti

Initially Deputy Country Manager, then Emergency Coordinator for the cholera outbreak

August 2010-January 2011

- Managing the MSF-OCA cholera response in Haiti
- Founding a collaboration with Google to map cholera cases
- MSF teams treated 110,000 cholera patients during my time as Head of Mission for one of the sections during the post-earthquake cholera intervention. Mortality without treatment was 40%, and in our facilities it was 0.9%. No other treatment was plausibly available to those patients. Therefore it is reasonable to assert that over 40,000 Haitians are alive today due to our efforts. This is not, of course, down to me; it was an enormous group effort, but I played a significant role, and of all the Key Performance Indicators or quantitative metrics of the work I have done in my life, it is the one of which I am most proud.

Robin B Clark Inc. Forestry Consultants

Occasional basis since 2001 (between humanitarian missions since 2003)

- Ecological restoration projects, generally with a focus on biodiversity, often with carbon sequestration implications.
- GIS and training.

MSF (OCA) Pakistan

July 2009-July 2010

Project Coordinator, Eastern Balochistan

Duties

 Negotiating access to an area of undeclared internal conflict in the eastern part of Pakistan's Balochistan province, where no foreign aid workers had been allowed for decades (partially successful)

MSF (OCA) Chad

August March-October 2008

Project Coordinator, Farchana

- Handing over a refugee/IDP/host population health program to local NGOs
- Keeping up the humanitarian character of the project until the end, did a fair bit of advocacy for the people in the camp
- Managing a fairly complex security context

MSF (OCA) Central African Republic

December 2005-January 2007

Logistician, Paoua, Boguila, Markounda (stint as Team Leader in Markounda)

MSF-Holland, Darfur, Sudan: Kalma camp (2 months) and Shariya town (4 months) Jan 2005-July 2005

Logistician, Watsan, and Admin

MSF-Holland, Burundi: Kinyinya Hospital Program – 6 months (Dec 2003 – June 2004)

Logistician Allround: From small support program to large full MSF hospital program.

Brinkman & Associates Reforestation Ltd.

1995-2003

Project manager, running forestry crews in Canada with up to 75 employees in remote locations.

Education and Training

Um, not so much, at least formally!

I have, on an occasional basis between humanitarian missions, undertaken approximately three years of full-time undirected (though credited) studies at Langara College and the University of British Columbia, both in Vancouver, Canada. Rather than taking a degree program I simply studied whatever interested me, which turned out to be biology, philosophy (mainly ethics along with a bit of formal logic), math, and some anthropology. I received very high grades in these classes, but never attempted to complete a degree as I was primarily interested in the learning and didn't feel I had time to take specific classes purely to complete degree requirements.

To this day I do quite a lot of undirected study, most of it online, but also mining the knowledge of my colleagues when involved in tech projects. I'm actually getting to the point where I'm a reasonably able

programmer; nowhere near Google software engineer caliber, but certainly able to have mutually useful conversations with "normal" programmers, and to be fairly effective in a product management role.

I'm able to build applications in Python and Java (including a bit of Android Java). Though I wouldn't pass an interview as an engineer complete with testing coverage and good coding style requirements, I can write useful small standalone utilities, and contribute useful code to larger projects (see Mapswipe in particular, where I wrote some mission-critical Python code). My bash scripting is quite good, and I'm a strong UNIX (well, GNU/Linux) system administration, with a particular focus on small, low-power and embedded systems, as these are the things most likely to function well in very resource-poor environments.

I've participated in a number of work-related training programs, mostly around project management and security.

I read Wikipedia a lot, as well as various technical publications and textbooks (currently working through Peter L. Dordal's incredible free and open textbook *An Introduction to Computer Networking*).

Languages

English: Mother tongue

French: Can sometimes pass for a native French Canadian. Don't enjoy writing formal documents in French (and very slow at it, not to mention with mediocre quality), but otherwise perfectly capable of normal written conversation.

Spanish: Can carry on a halfway intelligent conversation on most subjects, and once gave a reasonably coherent interview to a Spanish radio station from Nigeria

Italian: Can find the bathroom, order a beer, navigate, and guess accurately when I'm being insulted even without seeing the hand gestures

Latin: Very basic level, can usually figure out the meaning of a document or legal/medical phrase (aced the 101 level class in college and occasionally use it)

Arabic (North African colloquial): greetings, numbers, times, directions, simple requests and instructions. Once ran a vaccination clinic at the Chad/Libya border for a day without a translator, and it actually more or less worked.

Japanese: simple greetings and baby-talk (my 3-year-old daughter speaks English and Japanese, which forces me to keep up a bit)

Other Activities

Public speaking and advocacy: When not on mission I deliver speeches and presentations to various groups ranging from high schools and community groups to postgrad academic programs about humanitarian work, humanitarian technology, ethics, mapping, and migration policy.

Citizenship/Legal Status

Dual Canada/USA citizen, with valid passports from both countries. No criminal record or other problems.

Availability:

Looking for a job! Ideally something related to tech with operational impact in low-income/vulnerable settings. Open to other meaningful work.

Tech projects

github.com/ivangayton (in particular the ODKAggregateOnEdison project is a serious piece of functioning, complex bash scripting that's used in the real world), but a few of these projects are indicative of my mixed bag of skills; some horrible messes and some pretty good

<u>github.com/mapswipe/create-pybossa-tasks</u> (I wrote a bunch of this code along with Benni Herfort from the GIS unit at the University of Heidleberg)

mapswipe.org

projectbuendia.org

missingmaps.org (I conceived of and co-founded this project, shameless plug here: https://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/oct/06/missing-maps-human-genome-project-unmapped-cities)

References:

Drew Durbin, CEO, Wave.com drew@wave.com

Ka-Ping Yee, developer and team lead at Wave, ping@wave.com

Mike White, Operational Advisor at MSF (based in New York) michaelwhite@me.com

Pete Masters, Missing Maps coordinator at MSF-UK pete.masters@london.msf.org

Andrew Braye, GIS lead and co-founder of the Missing Maps project, British Red Cross. abraye@redcross.org.uk

Dr. Eric Perakslis, Senior Vice President, Informatics, Takeda Pharmaceuticals International Co., and executive director of the Center for Biomedical Informatics (CBMI) at Harvard Medical School Eric.Perakslis@takeda.com

Nigel Snoad, Product Manager at Verily (Google Life Sciences) nigelsnoad@google.com